Guide to the Ernie O'Malley Papers AIA.060
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series X. Diaries, Notes and Research, 1922-1963
  - Notebook: "I", circa 1932; cuid36800 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    Tan notebook with red binding containing research notes and original writings concerning the Irish revolutionary period in the early 20th century. Written by Ernie O'Malley while in New York City and used in future writings on the subject.
    This notebook contains 135 pages, 83 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "N", circa 1932 (Box 10, Folder 26)
    Blue notebook containing notes on English, French, and American literature, including works by Paul Verlaine, Thomas Wolfe, Herbert Read, and Daniel Defoe.
  - Notebook: "G", circa 1932-1935 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    Brown notebook with black binding containing research notes and writings on Irish folklore and sagas from Celtic Ireland.
  - Notebook: "Geography: Asia", circa 1930s (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Blue notebook with blue binding containing research notes concerning the Crusades and various countries in Asia, including Afghanistan, India, and Syria.
  - Notebook: "H": I, circa 1932-1935 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Blue notebook with blue binding containing writings concerning Irish history, folklore, and archaeology.
  - Notebook: "I": I, circa 1932-1935; cuid36801 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Blue notebook with blue binding containing research notes and writings concerning Irish history, with specific emphasis on ancient Ireland.
    This notebook contains 204 pages, 179 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "I": II, circa 1932-1935; cuid36802 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Blue notebook with blue binding containing research notes on Irish ballads, culture, literature, and historiography.
    This notebook contains 202 pages, 179 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "I": III, circa 1932-1935; cuid36803 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Brown notebook with black binding containing writings about and transcriptions of Irish folklore.
    This notebook contains 178 pages, 75 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "I": IV, circa 1932-1935; cuid36804 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Tan notebook containing research notes on books about Irish culture and literature.
    This notebook contains 166 pages, 149 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "I", circa 1932-1937 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    Blue notebook with blue binding containing research notes concerning Irish history, in addition to a list of Irish kings.
  - Notebook: "L", 1928 (Box 11, Folder 7A)
  - Notebook: "L/I": I, circa 1932-1935; cuid36805 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Blue notebook with blue binding containing research notes and writings concerning Irish authors and their works, including John Millington Synge, Lady Gregory, and William Butler Yeats.
    This notebook contains 202 pages, 76 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "L/I": II, circa 1932-1935; cuid36806 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Blue notebook with blue binding containing research notes and writings concerning Irish books, language, and proverbs.
    This notebook contains 203 pages, 113 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "LR", circa 1932-1935 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    Brown notebook with black binding containing research notes and writings concerning Frank O'Connor, John Hilton, Robert P. Tristram Coffin, and other writers.
  - Notebook "My/I", corca 1932-1935; cuid36807 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    Blue notebook with blue binding containing research notes and writings concerning Gaelic Irish literature, language, folklore, poetry, and cultural traditions.
    This notebook contains 205 pages, 102 of which have writing.
  - Notebook "N", circa Feb 1929 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    Grey notebook with blue binding containing research notes and writings concerning Leo Tolstoy, Fyodor Dostoyevsky, D.H. Lawrence, Carl Vam Vechten, T.S. Eliot, Lynn Riggs, Herman Melville, Edgar Saltus, Henry Black Fuller, Stephen Crane, and other writers. Notebook also contains diary entries from 1929 and a list of letters sent to Ireland during that time period.
  - Notebook "N": I, circa 1932-1935 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    Light blue notebook with dark blue binding containing writings on American, Irish, French, English, Belgian, Polish, and Russian authors, including Marcel Proust, Herman Melville, George Bernard Shaw, Hart Crane, and John Milton.
  - Notebook "N": II, circa 1932-1935; cuid36808 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    Blue notebook with blue binding containing writings on modern art and literature, including research notes on Gertrude Stein and Ernest Hemingway. Also includes critiques of Diego Rivera, William Faulkner, George Meredith, and Sherwood Anderson.
    This notebook contains 102 pages, 87 of which have writing.
  - Notebook "P", circa 1932-1935; cuid36809 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    Blue notebook containing research notes and writings on American poetry and imagism, with specific emphasis on works by Hart Crane, Emily Dickinson, Evelyn Scott, Marianne Moore, E.E. Cummings, Wallace Stevens, James Oppenheim, Carl Sandburg, Stanley Kunitz, Malcolm Cowley, and Robin Jeffers.
    This notebook contains 56 pages, 46 of which have writing.
  - Notebook "Russia", circa 1932-1935 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    Tan notebook with red binding containing writings on Russian literature, including works by Leo Tolstoy, Maxim Gorky, and Fyodor Dostoyevsky. Also includes some notes on French literature.
  - Notebook "Songs", circa 1927-1932 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    Blue notebook with blue binding containing writings on 17th century Irish history, in addition to transcriptions of traditional and Fenian Irish songs.
  - Notebook: untitled: I, circa 1932-1935 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    Blue notebook containing notes on Irish events and newspapers, in addition to time spent in New Mexico.
  - Notebook: untitled: II, circa 1932-1935; cuid36810 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    Brown notebook with black binding containing notes on James Joyce's Ulysses, in addition to writings concerning works by T.S. Eliot, William Butler Yeats, William Faulkner, Gertrude Stein, Padraic Colum, and Hart Crane.
    This notebook contains 132 pages, 95 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: untitled: III, circa 1932-1935; cuid36811 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    Tan notebook with red binding containig notes on works by American and Irish writers, including Ernest Hemingway, E.E. Cumings, T.S. Eliot, Gertrude Stein, James Joyce, Virginia Woolf, Padraic Colum, Peadar O'Donnell, and William Butler Yeats.
    This notebook contains 209 pages, 171 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: untitled: IV, circa 1932-1935 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    Brown patterned notebook with black binding containing notes on Irish historiography from 1916-1924, in addition to lists of books and transcriptions of poems and ballads.
  - Notebook: "Cat", circa 1932-1937 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    Green patterned notebook containing research notes and writings on poetry and listings of books arranged by subject and nationality.
  - Notebook: "E", circa 1932-1937 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    Green patterned notebook containing research notes and writings on French and English art.
  - Notebook: "G" artists, circa 1935-1937 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    Green patterned notebook containing commentary on European artists, including Albrecht Durer and Hans Holbein.
  - Notebook: "S", circa 1937 (Box 11, Folder 25)
    Green patterned notebook containing research notes, writings, and illustrations concerning Spanish art and artists.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1937 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    Green patterned notebook containing research notes and writings on Italian, Flemish, German, and English art history. Also includes illustrations and studies of individual paintings.
  - Notebook: "F", circa 1933 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Black and white patterned notebook containing sketches, illustrations, and research notes on art and artistics, including Vincent Van Gogh, Georges Seurat, Paul Gaugin, Henri Matisse, and Paul Cezanne.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1933-1934; cuid36812 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Orange notebook with black binding containing research notes and writings on early Irish history, poetry, and archaeology.
    This notebook contains 162 pages, 139 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "E", circa 1934 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    Brown notebook containing research notes on literature and poetry, including writings on William Shakespeare, Oscar Wilde, Robert Graves, and Fyodor Dostoyevksy.
  - Notebook: "I", circa 1935 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    Brown notebook containing research notes on books about Ireland, Irish proverbs, and works by William Butler Yeats and John Millington Synge.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1935-1936; cuid36813 (Box 12, Folder 4A)
    Red hardcover notebook containing book lists, research notes, and original writings concerning Irish history during the 1922-1923 time period.
    This notebook contains 263 pages, 152 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1935-1937 (Box 12, Folder 4B)
    Blue hardcover notebook containing transcribed ballads, news items, research notes, and original writings concerning the Irish Civil War,
  - Notebook: "I", circa 1935-1937 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Brown notebook with brown binding containing research notes and writings on Eoin MacNeill, Hugh Bolton, and various European playwrights.
  - Notebook: "L", circa 1935-1937 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    Brown notebook with brown binding containing notes on Celtic art, Austin Clarke, and American literature.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1935-1937 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    Navy leather pocket notebook containing lists of books, personal lists, Ernie O'Malley's schedule of classes at University College Dublin, and research notes on Christian art, military topics, and Sean Connolly.
  - Notebook: "I", circa 1936-1937 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    Green patterned notebook containing illustrations and research notes on Italian master artists Giorgione and Titian.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1936-1937 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    Red leather pocket notebook containig personal lists, lists of books, research notes on music, and medical school drawings by Ernie O'Malley.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1936-1938 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    Blue notebook containing writings and research notes on Asian culture, religion, and folklore.
  - Notebook: "P", circa 1937 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    Green patterned notebook containing writings and research notes on classical art from England, Flanders, France, Italy, Germany, and the Netherlands.
  - Notebook: "T", circa 1937 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    Green patterned notebook containing writings and research notes on painting techniques, use of color, and Romanesque art.
  - Notebook: "D", circa 1937-1938 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    Separated Materials
    Green patterned notebook containing writings on art history books, medieval paintings, Rembrant, and Dutch and French paintings.
  - Notebook: "FL", corca 1937-1938 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    Blue patterned notebook containing writings and research notes on works of European master artists.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1937-1938 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    Brown notebook containing notes on art history book and writings on the lives of various artists.
  - Notebook: "Mayo", circa 1937-1939 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    Green notebook containing writings and research notes on 16th and 17th century history of County Mayo, Ireland.
  - Notebook: "SP" "I", corca 1937-1939 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    Green notebook containing writings and research notes on 16th and 17th century history of western Ireland, with specific emphasis on County Mayo.
  - Notebook: "I" "P", circa 1938 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    Blue notebook containing writings and research notes on Renaissance, Baroque, Italian, and Flemish art, in addition to writings on artists such as Fra Angelico, Sandro Botticelli, and Jan van Eyck.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1938 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    Black notebook containing writings, illustrations, and research notes on Italian art, including works by El Greco and Vittore Carpaccio. Notebook also contains several versions of "The Last Supper."
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1938; cuid36814 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    Orange notebook containing writings, illustrations, and research notes about storytellers and local landmarks in Clew Bay, Co. Mayo. Notebook also contains writings on folklore and Pat Rooney.
    This notebook contains 79 pages, 60 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "Notes on books on Ireland": I, circa 1938-1939; cuid36815 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    Blue notebook containing writings and research notes on 16th and 17th century Irish history and archaeology.
    This notebook contains 160 pages, 71 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "Notes on books on Ireland": II, circa 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    Orange notebook containing writings and research notes on 16th and 17th century Irish history and archaeology.
  - Notebook: "SC 1589-93", circa 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 23)
    Green notebook containing writings and research notes on late 16th century Scottish history.
  - Notebook: "SC 1589-95", circa 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Notebook: "SC 1557-1603", circa 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 25)
    Green notebook containing writings and research notes on the Spanish Armada and its history in Ireland.
  - Notebook: "Researches in the S. of Ireland", circa 1938-1939; cuid36816 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Loose notebook containing writings and research notes on the history of southern Ireland.
    This notebook contains 252 pages, 119 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: untitled: I, circa 1938-1939; cuid36817 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Loose green notebook containing writings and research notes on 16th century Irish history.
    This notebook contains 214 pages, 122 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: untitled: II, circa 1938-1939; cuid36818 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    Loose green notebook containing lists of books about Irish history and culture, in addition to research notes on historical events, including the Spanish Armada.
    This notebook contains 188 pages, 99 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: untitled: III, circa 1938-1939; cuid36819 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Loose green notebook containing a bibliography of books on Irish history and culture.
    This notebook contains 114 pages, 60 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "Carew", circa 1938-1939 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Loose green notebook containing writings and notes about 16th century Irish history from research of Peter Carew papers.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1938 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Black notebook containing diary of trip to France, including lists of daily expenses and commentary on architectural features.
  - Notebook: untitled: I, circa 1939; cuid36820 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    Black notebook containing illustrations and research notes used in preparation for lectures on military tactics for Irish Defense Forces (IDF) during World War II. Includes notes for lecture for Local Defense Force in Cork.
    This notebook contains 228 pages, 73 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: untitled: II, circa 1939 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    Loose green notebook containing writings and research notes on 16th and 17th century Irish history.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1939-1944 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    Black pocket notebook containing research notes on music and lists of books and daily expenses.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1940-1942; cuid36821 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    Light blue notebook containing folklore and proverbs from Clew Bay, Co. Mayo and a listing of land Ernie O'Malley wished to purchase in Rosgibblin.
    This notebook contains 26 pages, 25 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "Studies on books", circa 1940-1944 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    Loose pink notebook containing research notes on English art and architecture.
  - Notebook: untitled: I, circa 1940-1949 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    Red notebook containing writings and research notes on American and English literature, including writings by William Butler Yeats, John Buchan, and Sir Walter Scott.
  - Notebook: untitled: II, circa 1940-1949; cuid36822 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    Blue notebook with green binding containing writings and research notes on archaeology, abbeys, and ancient architecture in Ireland, with illustrations and notes on Cistercian abbeys.
    This notebook contains 144 pages, 68 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: untitled: III, circa 1940-1949 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    Loose grey notebook containing lists of books and research notes on individuals in Galway, Sligo, and Mayo.
  - Notebook: untitled: IV, circa 1940-1949 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    Black notebook containing research notes on 16th and 17th century Ireland.
  - Notebook: "V", circa 1940-1949 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    Loose green notebook containing research notes on the Spanish Armada and 16th century Irish history.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1940-1950; cuid36827 (Box 13, Folder 16A)
    Notebook containing copies of correspondence, interview notes, research notes, and original writings concerning Irish history during the 1921-1923 time period.
    This notebook contains 178 pages, 139 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "I" "C" "3", circa 1942-1955; cuid36828 (Box 13, Folder 16B)
    Notebook containing research notes and original writings concerning Irish history during the 1920s, with specific emphasis on the Irish War of Independence.
    This notebook contains 200 pages, 147 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "A", circa 1942-1955 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    Tan notebook containing a listing of books in Ernie O'Malley's personal library organized by subjects, including paintings and music.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1944 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    Maroon pocket notebook containing a list of books concerning folklore and agriculture.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1944-1946 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    Green pocket notebook containing personal lists and notes on Dublin.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1945-1947 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Loose green notebook containing research notes on music, including specific composers, songs, symphonies, and movements.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1945-1948 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    Black notebook containing research notes on art history and literature, including medieval and Russian art and works by Manet, Roger Fry, and Impressionist painters.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1945-1950 (Box 14, Folder 2A)
    Notebook containing research notes concerning the holdings of the Irish Military Archives.
  - Notebook: "75", circa 1946 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1946-1948 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    Black pocket notebook containing sketches and research notes on clothing.
  - Notebook "Book III James Joyce", circa 1947-1948 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    Red notebook with black binding containing research notes and literary criticism on James Joyce's Ulysses and Finnegan's Wake, including commentary by other authors.
  - Notebook: "Book II James Joyce", circa 1947-1948 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Blue notebook with red binding containing research notes and literary criticism on James Joyce's Ulysses, including individuals, places, names, songs, and themes present.
  - Notebook: "Book I James Joyce", circa 1947-1948 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    Blue notebook with red binding containing research notes and literary criticism of James Joyce's Ulysses, including an index of places, names, songs, streets, and other details present.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1947-1950 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    Maroon pocket notebook containing research notes on Professor John V. Kelleher from Harvard, in addition to personal lists, lists of books, and a list of Jack B. Yeats paintings.
  - Notebook: "Irish Lit", circa 1950 (Box 14, Folder 8A)
    Pink hardcover notebook containing research notes on poetry, art history, Irish literature, including the works of William Butler Yeats, Lennox Robinson, George Bernard Shaw, John Millington Synge, Augustus John, John Rothenstein, Bernard Berenson, and Edith Sitwell.
  - Notebook: "Irish Painting", circa 1950-1957 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    Tan notebook containing writings and research notes on Irish paintings and artists, including Nano Reid, Norah McGuinness, Jack Hanlon, Patrick Hennessey, Louis le Brocquy, Margaret Clarke, and Basil Rakoczi.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1950-1957 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Notebook: "book lists", circa 1954 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Notebook: "Books", circa 1954 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    Cream notebook with tan binding containing an inventory of Ernie O'Malley's personal library preparated during his move fro mBurrishoole Lodge to Mespil Flats. Also includes an inventory of maps and illustrations on the arrangement of the bookshelves.
  - Notebook: "Irish Books / booklists", circa 1954 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Notebook: "Irish Lit", circa 1954 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    Ivory notebook with purple binding containing research notes on Irish literature, including writings about Lady Gregory, John Millington Synge, William Butler Yeats, and George Moore.
  - Notebook: "WR", circa 1954 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    Ivory notebook with purple binding containing notes of book read during the year and a lists of expenses for his travels in Paris.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1954 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    Black notebook with blue binding containing a listing of books in Ernie O'Malley's personal library organized by subject.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1954 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    Blue notebook with black binding containing an inventory of books in Ernie O'Malley's personal library while he lived at Mespil Flats.
  - Notebook: "Notes on Books on Mexico and Indians", circa 1954 (Box 14, Folder 17A)
  - Notebook: "American Indians", undated (Box 14, Folder 17B)
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1954 (Box 14, Folder 17C)
    Black hardcover notebook containing notes on Irish archaeology and archaeological journals.
  - Notebook: "Lit General", circa 1955 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    Pink notebook with red binding containing an inventory of Ernie O'Malley's personal library organized by country.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1955 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    Tan notebook containing an inventory of Ernie O'Malley's personal library organized by subject.
  - Notebook: "Book lists", circa 1955-1956 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    Tan notebook containing personal notes and notes on Ernie O'Malley's trip to Paris, including expenses and specific places to visit.
  - Notebook: "Book lists", circa 1956 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    Tan notebook containing an inventory of books listed by author, many concerning Ireland, history, and literature.
  - Notebook: "ART", circa 1956 (Box 14, Folder 21A)
    Notebook containing bibliography for the study of art and sculpture in Greece, France, Italy, Ireland, England, Spain, and Germany.
  - Notebook: untitled, circa 1956 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    Tan notebook containing address, lists of books, travel budgets, and notes for letters to Rebecca Citkowitz-Liber.
  - Notebook: "Armada", undated (Box 14, Folder 23)
    Loose green notebook containing lists of books read and research notes concerning the Spanish Armada.
  - Notebook: "Clare Ennis and Quinn Abbeys", undated; cuid36823 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Tan notebook with tan binding containing photographs, published writings, and annotations regarding early Christian art and architecture in Co. Clare, with specific emphasis on Ennis and Quinn Abbeys.
    This notebook contains 160 pages, 130 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "Clare", circa 1939, undated; cuid36824 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    Tan notebook with tan binding containing photographs, published writings, and annotations concerning early Christian art and architecture in Co. Clare.
    This notebook contains 236 pages, 206 of which have writing.
  - Notebook: "Cross Slabs", circa 1939, undated; cuid36825 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    Tan notebook with tan binding containing photographs, published writings, and annotations concerning early Christian art and architecture in Ireland.